Frances Porter Ticknor Papers, 1938-1990
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Frances Ticknor papers
1938-1990
Ticknor, Frances
MS 266
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA overseas official. The collection consists primarily of approximately 75 letters Ticknor wrote home to her family from Europe, Lebanon, and Egypt, describing her life and work overseas with the YWCA. In addition there are letters from friends; reports to the YWCA; and 39 photographs of her travels.
Frances Porter Ticknor was born July 19, 1912 in New Prague, Minnesota to Allen Harold and Edith Knowlton Porter. The family moved to Champaign, Illinois, where her father ran a bakery business. Following graduation from the University of Illinois in 1934, with a major in sociology and a minor in psychology, she did case work for emergency relief in Champaign-Urbana, IL. From 1935 to 1940 she was Girl Reserve Secretary and Camp Director for the YWCA in Rochester, Minnesota. In that capacity she attended the YWCA World Council Meeting in Muskoka, Ontario, Canada, in 1938 and also visited European YWCA camps in Belgium and the Netherlands as guest and visiting leader. She was YWCA delegate to the first World Christian Youth Conference in Amsterdam in 1939. Between 1940 and 1945, Ticknor served as YWCA Secretary for work with younger girls and as a camp director. Immediately after World War II she went abroad to help recovery in Belgium under the auspices of the National Board of the YWCA, which included three years work in Lebanon and Egypt. In 1948 she married Winton A. Ticknor and became a full time homemaker. They had five children and from 1955 onward lived in Lancaster, OH. She died June 12, 2007.
The Frances Porter Ticknor Papers consist of three linear inches (1 document box) of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and memorabilia. They consist primarily of approximately 75 letters she wrote home to her family from Europe, Lebanon, and Egypt, 1945-1948. They describe her life and work overseas with the YWCA. In addition there are letters (arranged alphabetically) to her from friends, 1940-90; reports to the YWCA, 1938, 1947; printed material about YWCA activities, 1939-47; and staff rosters, 1938-42. There are 39 photographs of her travels, the World Christian Youth Conference (1939) and YWCA World Council Meeting (1938).
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biography
II. Correspondence
III. YWCA
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any added restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Frances Porter Ticknor Papers were a gift of Ticknor in 1989 and 1991.
Search Terms
Ticknor, Frances; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A--History; Belgium--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Egypt--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Lebanon--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Syria--Social conditions--20th century--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL
  - Biographical background by FPT, clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Letters home from
    - Rochester, MN and Europe, 1938, 1945-47 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lebanon, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Egypt and en route home, 1947-48 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from friends, 1940-90 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters with International Interest Group of Antwerp, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES III. YWCA
  - Printed material, 1939-47 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reports, 1939, 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - YWCA staff rosters, 1938-42, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1939-48 (Box 1, Folder 10)